Guide to the E. L. Wolven Glass Plate Negative Collection, 1897-1944
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
E. L. Wolven Glass Plate Negative Collection
1897-1944
Wolven, Edmund L.
112 boxes (30 cubic feet)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
This collection includes 3,538 glass plate negatives created by photographer Edmund L. Wolven. Most of the images are of Vassar College people, events, buildings and grounds, but there is a subset that relates to Poughkeepsie and other local educational institutions.
Biographical Note
Edmund L. Wolven, born in Poughkeepsie in 1876, worked for many schools and colleges in the area. He began taking photographs for Vassar College in the late 1890s, and became the official college photographer between approximately 1900 and 1910.
Scope and Content Note
This collection includes 3,538 glass plate negatives created by photographer Edmund Wolven. Most of the images are of Vassar College people, events, buildings and grounds, but there is a subset that relates to other local educational institutions and Poughkeepsie.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into thirteen series: Series I. Athletics, 1902-1940; Series II. Buildings and Grounds, 1897-1940; Series III. Class Portraits, 1901-1943; Series IV. Commencement and Reunion, 1900-1942; Series V. Drama, Music, and Dance, 1900-1936; Series VI. Events and Festivals, 1915-1944; Series VII. Founder's Day, 1900-1935; Series VIII. Miscellaneous Vassar College Subjects, 1900-1940; Series IX. Non-Vassar, 1900-1929; Series X. Portraits of Individuals, circa 1910s - circa 1940; Series XI. Professor Fite's Reproductions, 1925; Series XII. Student Organizations, 1915-1936; and Series XIII. Vassar Paintings and Historical Images, 1900-1940.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Related Materials
E. L. Wolven Photograph Collection
Vassar College Photograph Files
Subject Headings
Organizations:
Alumnae and Alumni of Vassar College (Organization); Arlington (N.Y.:Township) Township Public Health Committee; Athletics; Institute for a Christian Basis of World Relations; Ku Klux Klan (1915- ); Lincoln Center (Poughkeepsie, N.Y.); Putnam Hall (Poughkeepsie, N.Y.); Riverview Military Academy (Poughkeepsie, N.Y.); St. Stephen's College (Annandale-on-Hudson, N.Y.); Vassar College--Alumni and Alumnae; Vassar College--Anniversaries, etc.; Vassar College--Archery; Vassar College--Baseball; Vassar College--Basketball; Vassar College--Buildings; Vassar College--Curricula; Vassar College--Employees; Vassar College--Faculty; Vassar College--Faculty housing; Vassar College--Fencing; Vassar College--Field hockey; Vassar College--Funds and scholarships; Vassar College--Golf; Vassar College--Hockey; Vassar College--Lacrosse; Vassar College--Societies and clubs; Vassar College--Sports; Vassar College--Student Housing; Vassar College--Swimming; Vassar College--Tennis; Vassar College--Track and field; Vassar College. Alumnae House; Vassar College. Athletic Circle; Vassar College. Blodgett Hall; Vassar College. Board of Trustees; Vassar College. Chapel; Vassar College. Choir; Vassar College. Christian Association; Vassar College. Class of 1867; Vassar College. Class of 1868; Vassar College. Class of 1870; Vassar College. Class of 1872; Vassar College. Class of 1873; Vassar College. Class of 1874; Vassar College. Class of 1876; Vassar College. Class of 1878; Vassar College. Class of 1879; Vassar College. Class of 1881; Vassar College. Class of 1882; Vassar College. Class of 1884; Vassar College. Class of 1885; Vassar College. Class of 1886; Vassar College. Class of 1887; Vassar College. Class of 1888; Vassar College. Class of 1890; Vassar College. Class of 1891; Vassar College. Class of 1892; Vassar College. Class of 1893; Vassar College. Class of 1894; Vassar College. Class of 1895; Vassar College. Class of 1896; Vassar College. Class of 1897; Vassar College. Class of 1898; Vassar College. Class of 1899; Vassar College. Class of 1900; Vassar College. Class of 1901; Vassar College. Class of 1902; Vassar College. Class of 1903; Vassar College. Class of 1904; Vassar College. Class of 1905; Vassar College. Class of 1906; Vassar College. Class of 1907; Vassar College. Class of 1908; Vassar College. Class of 1909; Vassar College. Class of 1910; Vassar College. Class of 1911; Vassar College. Class of 1912; Vassar College. Class of 1913; Vassar College. Class of 1914; Vassar College. Class of 1915; Vassar College. Class of 1916; Vassar College. Class of 1917; Vassar College. Class of 1918; Vassar College. Class of 1919; Vassar College. Class of 1920; Vassar College. Class of 1921; Vassar College. Class of 1922; Vassar College. Class of 1923; Vassar College. Class of 1924; Vassar College. Class of 1925; Vassar College. Class of 1926; Vassar College. Class of 1927; Vassar College. Class of 1928; Vassar College. Class of 1929; Vassar College. Class of 1930; Vassar College. Class of 1931; Vassar College. Class of 1932; Vassar College. Class of 1933; Vassar College. Class of 1934; Vassar College. Class of 1935; Vassar College. Class of 1936; Vassar College. Class of 1937; Vassar College. Class of 1938; Vassar College. Class of 1939; Vassar College. Class of 1940; Vassar College. Class of 1941; Vassar College. Class of 1942; Vassar College. Class of 1943; Vassar College. Class of 1944; Vassar College. Class of 1945; Vassar College. Class of 1945-4; Vassar College. Davison Hall; Vassar College. Department of English; Vassar College. Department of French; Vassar College. Department of German; Vassar College. Department of Latin; Vassar College. Dramatic Workshop; Vassar College. Glee Club; Vassar College. Goodfellowship Club; Vassar College. International Club; Vassar College. Italian Club; Vassar College. Kendrick Hall; Vassar College. Kenyon Hall; Vassar College. Library; Vassar College. Main Building; Vassar College. Mandolin Club; Vassar College. Miscellany News; Vassar College. Observatory; Vassar College. Octette; Vassar College. Orchestra; Vassar College. Philalethean Society; Vassar College. Raymond House; Vassar College. Rockefeller Hall; Vassar College. Sextette; Vassar College. Skinner Hall; Vassar College. Students Building; Vassar College. Taylor Hall; Vassar College. Vassar Players; Vassar College. Vassar Workshop; Vassar College. Williams House; Yale University--Field hockey
Subjects:
Academic rites and ceremonies; Astronomy--Study and teaching; Blackface; Brownface; Children's theater; Christmas plays; College students--Social life and customs; College theater; Halloween; Horsemanship--Competitions; Ice industry; Landscapes; Liberty bonds; May Day; Peace movements; Redface; Skating; Social settlements; Stained glass windows; Stereotypes (social psychology); Tapestry, Flemish; Winter sports; World War (1914-1918)--Social aspects; Yellowface
Names:
Appasamy, E. S.; Baldwin, James Fosdick, 1871-; Bishop, Harriette Warner, 1845-1944; Blatch, Harriot Stanton, 1856-1940; Bowman, Winifred Comstock, 1904-1991; Buck, Gertrude, 1871-1922; Burroughs, John, 1837-1921; Butler of Saffron Walden, Richard Austen Butler, Baron, 1902-1982; Chappell, George S. (George Shepard), 1877-1946; Coonley, Queene Ferry; Cornaro Piscopia, Elena Lucrezia, 1646-1684; Duggan, Stephen, 1870-1950; Fitch, Robert F. (Robert Ferris), 1873-; Fite, Emerson David, 1874-1953; Furness, Caroline E. (Caroline Ellen), 1869-1936; Gow, George Coleman, 1860-1938; Heinlein, Mary Virginia; Inman, Samuel Guy, 1877-1965; Johnson, Burgess, 1877-1963; Jordan, Mary A. (Mary Augusta), 1855-1941; Kendrick, Georgia Avery, 1848-1922; Kenyon, Helen; Lathrop, Julia Clifford, 1858-1932 |; Lyman, Hannah, 1816-1871; MacCracken, H. N. (Henry Noble), 1880-1970; McCaleb, Ella, 1856-1933; Millay, Edna St. Vincent, 1892-1950; Mills, Herbert Elmer, 1861-1946; Mitchell, Maria, 1818-1889; Nettleton, George Henry, 1874-1959; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945; Ross, Caroline S. Barnes, 1883-1960; Ryan, W. Carson (Will Carson), 1885-1968; Salmon, Lucy Maynard, 1853-1927; Semple, Ellen Churchill, 1863-1932; Shujing, Ding; Smiley, Daniel, 1855-1930; Sparrow, Gerald, 1903-1988; Taylor, James Monroe, 1848-1916; Thompson, C. Mildred (Clara Mildred), 1881-1975; Tiffany, Louis Comfort, 1848-1933; Vassar, Matthew, 1792-1868; Whitmarsh, Esther; Whitney, Mary Watson, 1847-1921; Woodward, Helen Douglas, 1842-1941; Wylie, Laura Johnson, 1855-1932
Places:
Poughkeepsie (N.Y.)--Buildings, structures, etc.
VCL Categories:
Audiovisuals and Realia
Encoding Information
Encoded by Laura Streett, 2024.
Other Formats
The E. L. Wolven Glass Plate Negative Collection has been digitized and is available to view online in the Vassar College Digital Library. Each negative has a corresponding identification number, which can be seen in square brackets next to the negative's physical box number on the container list below. Inputing this identification number in the Digital Library search bar will result in the corresponding negative.
Series List
- Series I. Athletics, 1902-1940; [508 plates]
  This series consists of photographs of athletics activities and events at Vassar College, including almost yearly images of Field Day from 1916-1936; team portraits and action photographs from field hockey, basketball, baseball, tennis, fencing, lacrosse, and archery events. There are also images from horse shows, golfing, swimming, and winter sports. Topics documented in this series include the evolution of women's uniforms, as well as developments in athletic fields and equipment.
  Organized into subseries by subject and sub-arranged chronologically.
- Series II. Buildings and Grounds, 1897-1940; [141 plates]
  This series consists of images of Vassar College buildings (interior and exterior) and the landscapes of the campus and surrounding area. Highlights include views of Vassar Lake before the Raymond Avenue elevation change in 1966, the southeast portion of campus before Sunset Lake was created, Raymond Avenue before the Faculty Row houses were built, the living and research spaces in the Maria Mitchell Observatory, and maintenance staff harvesting ice with saws and horse-drawn ice plows.
- Series III. Class Portraits, 1901-1943; [120 plates]
  This series contains freshman and senior class portraits from a selection of graduating classes between 1901 and 1943. The images were taken using extra large plates (14 x 17 inches) which provides access to fine details and allows for easier identification of individuals.
  Arranged chronologically by class year.
- Series IV. Commencement and Reunion, 1900-1942; [711 plates]
  In the first half of the 20th century, Vassar's commencement and reunion were part of a 4-5 day long celebration that included a variety of events and traditions. Steady events included Baccalaureate Sunday, the alumnae parade, Class Day exercises, and commencement. Other activities changed over the decades, and included concerts and lectures, luncheons and suppers, tree ceremonies, May Pole dances, and for many years the III Hall Play was repeated for families and alumnae.
  This series consists primarily of images from commencement, Class Day exercises, and the alumnae parade. Photos of Sophomores picking daisies for the Daisy Chain are also included. Early graduates and significant alumnae such as Harriette Warner Bishop and Helen D. Woodward (both VC 1867), Mary Augusta Jordan (VC 1876), Harriot Stanton Blatch (VC 1878), Julia Lathrop (VC 1880), and Blanche Ferry Hooker (VC 1894) are pictured; as are faculty, administrators and trustees such as C. Mildred Thompson, Ella McCaleb, Herbert E. Mills, and the astronomers Caroline Furness and Mary Whitney.
- Series V. Drama, Music, and Dance, 1900-1936; [1,414 plates]
  This series consists of images of plays, skit shows, dance performances, and musical events. It comprises the largest series in the Wolven collection. Junior and sophomore parties were generally skit shows written by students. These events included racist and stereotypical costumes and performances, including use of blackface. The major dramatic productions ("Hall" plays) include previously produced pieces, as well as material written by students, faculty, and alumnae, including Edna St. Vincent Millay.
  Arranged chronologically.
- Series VI. Events and Festivals, 1915-1944; [131 plates]
  This series includes images of events that were not as large or well-photographed as Field Day, Founder's Day, and commencement and reunion activities. The annual class tree ceremonies, proms, 50th college anniversary, maypole dances, conferences, protests, community work, and other activities are included. Highlights include pageants and performances from the College's 50th Anniversary celebrations, the 1924 Institute for a Christian Basis of World Relations, and 1920's Township Day, which welcomed Arlington children to campus to participate in athletics and dramatic performances.
- Series VII. Founder's Day, 1900-1935; [1,300 plates]
  This series consists of images of Founder's Day, an annual Vassar College tradition that has included a variety of activities since the first celebration on April 29th, 1866--Matthew Vassar's birthday. The images in this series document visits to the founder's grave, step-singing and the Song Contest, the faculty-student baseball game, parades, and various performances. Attendees of the baseball game, the parades, and the performances were encouraged to dress in costume, according to either a predetermined theme or individual whim. With some frequency, these costumes and performances were based on racist or stereotypical representations of marginalized groups, including blackface, redface, and yellowface. Similarly, the faculty play or skit show which was given on the evening of Founder's Day, included racist and stereotypical costumes and performances.
  Organized into subseries by year or year group, and sub-arranged alphabetically by title.
- Series VIII. Miscellaneous Vassar College Subjects, 1900-1940; [118 plates]
  This series consists of additional subjects related to Vassar College that do not fall under any previous series. Selected highlights from this set include group portraits of the Good Fellowship Club men's and women's basketball teams, a classroom scene of a "preparedness course" on shorthand taught shortly after the U.S. entered World War I, and students working at Lincoln Center, the Poughkeepsie organization that assisted the poor.
  Arranged roughly in chronological order.
- Series IX. Non-Vassar, 1900-1929; [20 plates]
  This series includes Wolven's portraits of classes at St. Stephen's College (now Bard College), the Putnam School, and Riverview Military Academy, as well as views of Poughkeepsie streets and landscapes, including the Mid-Hudson Bridge while it was under construction.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject.
- Series X. Portraits of Individuals, circa 1910s - circa 1940; [30 plates]
  This series consists of portraits of individuals, including Vassar College students and faculty. Most individuals pictured are unidentified.
  Arranged alphabetically by name or subject.
- Series XI. Professor Fite's Reproductions, 1925; [23 plates]
  This series consists of photographs of reproductions of historical documents for political science and history professor Emerson David Fite.
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
- Series XII. Student Organizations, 1915-1936; [75 plates]
  This series consists of group portraits of student organizations taken for the Vassar College yearbook and to be sold as souvenirs. Portraits of the athletic teams are included in Series I. Athletics. The groups in this series include the Vassar College Choir, the Glee Club, the Mandolin Club, class officers, and the staff of various student publications.
  Organized into subseries alphabetically by subject, and sub-arranged chronologically.
- Series XIII. Vassar Paintings and Historical Images, 1900-1940; [19 plates]
  This series consists of photographs of portraits of Matthew Vassar, his family, and other individuals related to the college's early history.
Container List
- Series I. Athletics, 1902-1940
  - Archery
    - Archery team portrait — Archery team, 1932 (Box 37/38 [Box271_001])
    - Archery practice — Five archery students in the circle near Students Building, 1936 (Box 37/38 [Box271_014])
  - Basketball
    - Basketball team portrait — Group portrait of the Class of 1904 basketball team (left to right): Mary B. Gentry, Sarah B. Converse, Katherine M. Botsford, Frances S. Beckwith, Maud Florence Hunt, Lucile Hinkle Stimson, Katharine M. Cloak, Annie Wyman Wood. Copy of an image similar to one taken for the 1903 Vassarion by the photographers Fritz and Dean, 1902-1903 (Box 5 [Package019_004])
    - Basketball players — Copy photograph of students from the Class of 1904 and the Class of 1908 in gym suits on an outdoor basketball court (Box 5 [Package019_010])
    - Basketball team portrait — Class of 1911 basketball team, 1909-1910 (Box 92 [Box251_023])
    - Basketball game — Basketball game, Class of 1913 versus the Class of 1914, 1910-1913 (Box 39/40 [Box274_018])
    - Basketball game — Basketball game, Class of 1913 versus the Class of 1914, 1910-1913 (Box 39/40 [Box274_020])
    - Basketball game — Basketball game, including members of the Class of 1913, 1910-1913 (Box 39/40 [Box274_016])
    - Basketball game — Basketball game in field in front of Students Building, including members of the Class of 1916, Early 1910s (Box 39/40 [Box274_023])
    - Basketball game — Basketball game, including members of the Class of 1914, 1911-1914 (Box 39/40 [Box274_017])
    - Basketball game — Basketball game in field in front of Students Building, including members of the Class of 1916, 1913-1916 (Box 13 [Package088_010])
    - Basketball game — Basketball game, Class of 1914 versus the Class of 1915 (Box 39/40 [Box274_021])
    - Basketball game — Basketball game, Class of 1914 versus the Class of 1915 (Box 39/40 [Box274_022])
    - Basketball game — Basketball game, 1916 (Box 13 [Package088_008])
    - Basketball game — Basketball game, 1916 (Box 13 [Package088_012])
    - Basketball game — Basketball game, Class of 1917 versus the Class of 1919, 1916-1917 (Box 39/40 [Box274_015])
    - Basketball game — Basketball game, Class of 1917 versus the Class of 1919, 1916-1917 (Box 39/40 [Box274_019])
    - Basketball game — Basketball game, Class of 1917 versus the Class of 1919, 1916-1917 (Box 13 [Package088_007])
    - Basketball game — Basketball game, Class of 1917 versus the Class of 1919, 1916-1917 (Box 13 [Package088_009])
    - Basketball game — Basketball game, Class of 1917 versus the Class of 1919, 1916-1917 (Box 13 [Package088_011])
    - Basketball team portrait — Class of 1916 basketball team, 1916-1917 (Box 92/93 [Box252_006])
    - Basketball team portrait — Class of 1917 basketball team, 1916-1917 (Box 92/93 [Box252_005])
    - Basketball team portrait — Class of 1918 basketball team, 1916-1917 (Box 91/92 [Box250_023])
    - Basketball team portrait — Class of 1917 basketball team, 1917-1918 (Box 63 [203_14])
    - Basketball team portrait — Class of 1921 basketball team, 1919-1920 (Box 57 [package138e])
    - Basketball team portrait — Class of 1922 basketball team, 1919-1920 (Box 57 [package138b])
    - Basketball team portrait — Varsity basketball team, 1920 (Box 57 [package138d])
    - Basketball team portrait — Class of 1922 basketball team (Box 67 [210_11])
    - Basketball team portrait — Class of 1923 basketball team, 1922 (Box 67 [210_10])
    - Basketball team portrait — Class of 1924 basketball team, 1922 (Box 67/68 [211_05])
    - Basketball team portrait — Class of 1925 basketball team, 1922 (Box 67 [210_02])
    - Basketball team portrait — Varsity basketball team, 1922 (Box 67 [210_09])
    - Basketball team portrait — Class of 1923 basketball team, 1922-1923 (Box 92/93 [Box252_020])
    - Basketball team portrait — Class of 1924 basketball team, 1922-1923 (Box 92/93 [Box252_018])
    - Basketball team portrait — Class of 1925 basketball team, 1922-1923 (Box 92/93 [Box252_017])
    - Basketball team portrait — Class of 1926 basketball team, 1922-1923 (Box 92/93 [Box252_021])
    - Basketball team portrait — Class of 1926 basketball team, 1922-1923 (Box 92/93 [Box252_022])
    - Basketball team portrait — Varsity basketball team, 1922-1923 (Box 92/93 [Box252_016])
    - Basketball team portrait — Class of 1924 basketball team, approximately 1923 (Box 70/71 [216_12])
    - Basketball team portrait — Class of 1925 basketball team, approximately 1923 (Box 70/71 [216_24])
    - Basketball team portrait — Class of 1926 basketball team, approximately 1923 (Box 70/71 [216_13])
    - Basketball team portrait — Class of 1926 basketball team, approximately 1923 (Box 70/71 [216_23])
    - Basketball team portrait — Class of 1927 basketball team, approximately 1923 (Box 70/71 [216_14])
    - Basketball team portrait — Varsity basketball team, approximately 1923 (Box 70/71 [216_15])
    - Basketball team portrait — Class of 1925 basketball team (Box 77/78 [229_12])
    - Basketball team portrait — Class of 1926 basketball team, 1925 (Box 77/78 [229_15])
    - Basketball team portrait — Class of 1927 basketball team, 1925 (Box 77/78 [229_14])
    - Basketball team portrait — Class of 1928 basketball team, 1925 (Box 77/78 [229_13])
    - Basketball team portrait — Class of 1928 basketball team, 1925 (Box 77/78 [229_16])
    - Basketball team portrait — Varsity basketball team, 1925 (Box 77/78 [229_11])
    - Basketball team portrait — Class of 1926 basketball team, 1925-1926 (Box 67/68 [211_01])
    - Basketball team portrait — Class of 1927 basketball team, 1925-1926 (Box 67/68 [211_19])
    - Basketball team portrait — Class of 1928 basketball team, 1925-1926 (Box 67/68 [211_02])
    - Basketball team portrait — Class of 1929 basketball team, 1925-1926 (Box 67/68 [211_18])
    - Basketball team portrait — Varsity basketball team, 1925-1926 (Box 67/68 [211_13])
    - Basketball team portrait — Class of 1927 basketball team, 1926-1927 (Box 67/68 [211_04])
    - Basketball team portrait — Class of 1928 basketball team, 1926-1927 (Box 80/81 [235_18])
    - Basketball team portrait — Class of 1928 basketball team, 1926-1927 (Box 80/81 [235_20])
    - Basketball team portrait — Class of 1930 basketball team, 1926-1927 (Box 80/81 [235_10])
    - Basketball team portrait — Class of 1930 basketball team, 1926-1927 (Box 80/81 [235_14])
    - Basketball team portrait — Class of 1928 basketball team, 1927-1928 (Box 57 [package140c])
    - Basketball team portrait — Class of 1928 basketball team, 1927-1928 (Box 57 [package140d])
    - Basketball team portrait — Class of 1929 basketball team, 1927-1928 (Box 57 [package138h])
    - Basketball team portrait — Class of 1929 basketball team, 1927-1928 (Box 57 [package140])
    - Basketball team portrait — Class of 1930 basketball team, 1927-1928 (Box 57 [package140f])
    - Basketball team portrait — Class of 1931 basketball team, 1927-1928 (Box 57 [package140b])
    - Basketball team portrait — Varsity basketball team, 1927-1928 (Box 57 [package140e])
    - Basketball team portrait — Class of 1929 basketball team, 1928-1929 (Box 92 [Box251_012])
    - Basketball team portrait — Class of 1929 basketball team, 1928-1929 (Box 92 [Box251_013])
    - Basketball team portrait — Class of 1929 basketball team, 1928-1929 (Box 92 [Box251_014])
    - Basketball team portrait — Class of 1930 basketball team, 1928-1929 (Box 92 [Box251_016])
    - Basketball team portrait — Class of 1930 basketball team, 1928-1929 (Box 92 [Box251_020])
    - Basketball team portrait — Class of 1931 basketball team, 1928-1929 (Box 92 [Box251_018])